Guide to the Eugene O'Neill Papers Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Eugene O'Neill papers addition
1852-1951
1920-1940
YCAL MSS 597
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(6 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
The Eugene O'Neill papers addition contains correspondence, financial and legal records, and other materials relating to American playwright Eugene O'Neill and his wife Carlotta O'Neill. Correspondence consists of incoming correspondence only, chiefly to Eugene O'Neill, though there are also letters addressed to Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill jointly and to Carlotta. Correspondents include theater figures Virgil Geddes, Robert Edmond Jones, Kenneth Macgowan, and George Jean Nathan. Financial and legal records consist chiefly of financial records relating to Eugene O'Neill, such as bills and receipts and stock statements, but there are also legal records relating to O'Neill's parents, James and Ella O'Neill. Other materials include clippings, photographs, and printed ephemera.
O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of McIntosh and Otis, Inc., 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Eugene O'Neill Papers (YCAL MSS 123), Eugene O'Neill Collection (YCAL MSS 124), and Agnes Bolton Collection of Eugene O'Neill (YCAL MSS 122).
Eugene O'Neill (1888-1953)
A biographical timeline is provided in the Eugene O'Neill Papers (YCAL MSS 123).
Scope and Contents
The Eugene O'Neill Papers Addition contains correspondence, financial and legal records, and other materials relating to American playwright Eugene O'Neill and his wife Carlotta O'Neill. Correspondence consists of incoming correspondence only, chiefly to Eugene O'Neill, though there are also letters addressed to Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill jointly and to Carlotta. Correspondents include theater figures Virgil Geddes, Robert Edmond Jones, Kenneth Macgowan, and George Jean Nathan, among others. Financial and legal records consist chiefly of financial records relating to Eugene O'Neill, such as bills and receipts and stock statements, but there are also legal records relating to O'Neill's parents, James and Ella O'Neill. Other materials include clippings, photographs, printed ephemera, and a suitcase. Clippings relate chiefly to Eugene O'Neill, his father James O'Neill, and literary matters. Photographs include snapshots and studio portraits of Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill and others.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1927-1948. II. Financial and Legal Records, 1880-1949. III. Other Materials, 1852-1951.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Geddes, Virgil, 1897-1989; Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954; Macgowan, Kenneth, 1888-1963; Nathan, George Jean, 1882-1958; O'Neill, Carlotta; O'Neill, Ella, -1922; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953; O'Neill, James, 1847-1920
- Correspondence, 1927-1948; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name or supplied heading (in brackets).
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence consists of incoming correspondence only, chiefly to Eugene O'Neill, though there are also letters addressed to Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill jointly and to Carlotta. Correspondents include theater figures Virgil Geddes, Robert Edmond Jones, Kenneth Macgowan, and George Jean Nathan, among others.
  Chiefly in English, with some letters in French.
  - "A" general, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "B" general, 1931-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brennan, Agnes, 1932-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bouché, [C. E.?], 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "C" general, 1928-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Carlin, Terry, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Chickens], 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clark, Barrett H., 1929-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clark, William H.; Croake, Jack, 1930-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Crouse, Russell, 1934-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "D" general, 1927-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Dramatists Guild, 1936-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Draper, George, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Duvivier, Joseph, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "E" general, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Elkins, Felton, 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Federal Theatre Project, 1936-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [Foreign letters], 1927-1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Francis, John A., 1927-1932 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "G" general, 1928-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
    Includes letters from Virgil Geddes
  - [Germany], 1932 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "H" general, 1928-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Havre, J. B., 1937-1948 (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
  - Howard, Sidney, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "I" general, 1941 January 23 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Irish Academy of Letters, 1938-1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "J" general, 1947 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Jones, Robert Edmond, 1933-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Includes drawings
  - "K" general, 1929-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - "L" general, 1929-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
  - "M" general, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Macgowan, Kenneth, 1936-1947 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - [Mourning Becomes Electra], 1931-1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - "N" general, 1937-1946 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Nathan, George Jean, 1935-1948 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - [Nobel Prize], 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 48-50)
  - [Nuts], 1930, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - "O" general, 1936-1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - O'Neill, Carlotta, 1935-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Includes photographs
  - "P" general, 1933-1948 (Box 3, Folder 54-55)
  - [Plagarism suit], 1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Prokosch, Frederic, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - "R" general, 1939-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - [Requests], 1943 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - "S" general, 1929-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
  - Sisk, Robert, 1928-1947, undated (Box 4, Folder 62-63)
  - Skinner, R. Dana, 1934-1941 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Stram, Cynthia, 1932-1948, undated (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
  - [Strange Interlude], 1927-1931, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - "T" general, 1933-1944 (Box 4, Folder 68-69)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1935-1946 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - "W" general, 1940-1946, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - "Y" general, 1937-1948 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Empty folders, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
- Financial and Legal Records, 1880-1949; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by folder heading.
  Series II.Financial and Legal Records consists chiefly of financial records relating to Eugene O'Neill, including bills and receipts and stock statements, but there are also legal records relating to Eugene O'Neill's parents, James and Ella O'Neill.
  - Autos, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Bills and receipts, 1928-1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 76-78)
  - Contributions, 1946-1948, undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Ella O'Neill's will, undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Financial and legal papers, 1926-1949, undated (Box 5, Folder 81-82)
  - Financial statements, 1929-1934, undated (Box 5, Folder 83-84)
  - Foreign rights statements, 1928-1934, undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - James O'Neill material, 1880-1921, undated (Box 5, Folder 86-87)
  - Pell quarterly statements, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Stock [statements], 1935-1943 (Box 5, Folder 89-94)
- Other Materials, 1852-1951; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III. Other Materials contains clippings, photographs, printed ephemera, and other material. Clippings relate chiefly to Eugene O'Neill, his father James O'Neill, and literary matters. Photographs include snaphots and studio portraits of Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill and others.
  - Clippings, 1852-1948, undated (Box 6, Folder 95-98)
  - [Little papers], 1928-1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 99-100)
    Includes correspondence, financial records, printed ephemera, and other papers
  - Photographs, 1922-1943, undated (Box 6, Folder 101-110)
    Includes photographs by Carl Van Vechten and others
  - Writings, 1917, undated (Box 6, Folder 111)
    Includes extracts from "The Strange Interlude" (photostat) and "Notes on the Dramatic Material for a Play on Chin Shin Huang"
- Oversize, 3
  - [Mourning Becomes Electra] (Box 7 broadside folder)
  - Clippings (Box 8 broadside folder)
  - [Little papers] (Box 9 broadside folder)